Guide to the Henry N. Ricciuti papers, 1946-2008.
Ricciuti, Henry N. papers, 1946-2008.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Henry N. Ricciuti papers, 1946-2008.
23-13-2551
Henry N. Ricciuti
8.5 cubic ft.
Files.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Files relating to the career of Henry N. Ricciuti, Professor of Human Development and Family Studies in the New York State College of Human Ecology.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Human Development and Family Studies, New York State College of Human Ecology.
Henry Ricciuti earned his B.S., M.A. and Ph.D. (1949), all in psychology from Fordham University, and served in the U.S. Army from 1943 to 1946. Prior to joining the Cornell faculty in 1958, he served as an assistant professor at the University of Connecticut, research associate at the Educational Testing Service, and assistant professor at the University of Colorado Medical School. At Cornell, he was a professor in the Dept. of Human Development and Family Studies (1958-1988), specialized in early childhood development, especially the factors associated with cognitive and emotional development of infants and young children. He was an active emeritus professor from 1988-2011.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Files relating to the reorganization of the College of Human Ecology, particularly the Reorganization Committee, chaired by Dr. Ricciuti; files relating to his membership on the Faculty Committee on Student Affairs, 1966-1969, with much material on events leading up to the Straight takeover in April 1969; and materials relating to Cornell's involvement with day care, starting with the Cornell Day Care Committee, 1971-1972; the Cornell-Tompkins County Day Care Project, 1972-1974; the Infant Care and Resource Center, operated in Sage Infirmary, 1975-1980, under a grant from the Appalachian Regional Commission; and the unsuccessful efforts to continue to offer work-site infant day care on campus.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ricciuti, Henry N.; Cornell Day Care Committee.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University--Faculty.; Cornell University. Faculty Committee on Student Affairs.; Cornell University. Infant Care and Resource Center.; Cornell-Tompkins County Day Care Project.; New York State College of Human Ecology.; National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (U.S.).
Subjects:
Employer-supported day care.; Day care centers--New York (State)--Ithaca.; African American student movements--New York (State)--Ithaca.; Students--Political activity.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. College of Home Economics Organization Committee
Series II. Faculty Committee on Student Affairs (FCSA)
Series III. Infant Day Care and Resource Center
Series IV. Cornell-Tompkins Day Care Project
Series V. University Related Files
Series VI. Department Related Files
Series VII. International Programs
Series VIII. College Related Files
Series IX. Proposals, Studies, Research
Series X. Photographs
Series XI. Publications
Series XII. Correspondence
Series XIII. Subject Files
Series XIV. National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. College of Home Economics Organization Committee
  - College Organization Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - College Organization Committee, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dean's Committee on Reorganization, 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
  - Reorganization Committee, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - College Study Reports and Faculty Actions, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Organization Committee Report - first copy, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Factual Data - general, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Department Reactions to Organization, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Organization Committee - Textiles and Clothing, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - Organization Committee - Extension, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "Summary of Programmatic & Structural Changes in the College 1965 - 1970" written by Ricciuti, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15A)
- Series II. Faculty Committee on Student Affairs (FCSA)
  - FCSA, 1966-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - FCSA, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 19-24)
  - Student Code, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - FCSA, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 27-30)
- Series III. Infant Day Care and Resource Center
  - Correspondence - local: Tompkins County/Cornell University Infant Care and Resource Center, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Infant Day Care and Resource Center - original proposal, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Infant Day Care and Resource Center - second year proposal, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Series IV. Cornell-Tompkins Day Care Project
  - Cornell-Tompkins Day Care Project, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
  - Report and Recommendations of the Cornell-Tompkins Day Care Project, August 1974 (Box 1)
  - Day Care Project, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Day Care Project - Task Force, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Day Care Project - report, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Proposal to Establish Infant Care and Resource Center, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Day Care Committee, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Day Care Proposal, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series V. University Related Files
- Minority Education Committee, 1999-2003 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Ombudsman Position, 1986-1994 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Weiss Fellowship Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Emeritus Professor Tutorial Project, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Cornell '69 in Retrospect, May 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Emeritus PC Computer Workshop, 1996-1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Emeritus-One-on-One Computer Help, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- CAPE-Survey of Emeritus Faculty, 1999-2002, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- CAPE-Survey Concerning Office Space, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Series VI. Department Related Files
- Chair-correspondence, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Chair-correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Graduate Field Matters, 1980-1982; 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- A.D. White Professorship, 1985-1991 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Corporate Child Care Venture, 1986-1989 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Proposed Developmental Sciences Program, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Chair-Department Issues, 1989-1996 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Chair Search, 19December 1990-January 1991 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Department Review and Structure, 1988-1997 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Affirmative Action-Recruiting Faculty-Black Caucus of the Society for Research in Child Development, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Acting Department Chair (Appointment of Steve Robertson as Chair), Summer 1997 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Chair Search, Spring 1997 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Department Governance Statement, 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Early Childhood Center; Changes in Nursery School, 1997-2002 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Series VII. International Programs
- Bogota and Follow-up, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Visit to Caracas and Follow-up, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Visits to Caracas, 1980, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Series VIII. College Related Files
- Correspondence with Dean/Provost David Knapp, 1972-1977 (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Pre-Med Minority Students-Cornell Medical Summer Fellowship Program, 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Summer Minority Fellowships-Cornell-City College of New York, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Minority Student Recruitment and Retention Report, 1988-1989 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Minority Summer Fellowships-Cornell/Hunter, 1990-1992 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Affirmative Action Planning, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- MARC Program, 1991, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Undergraduate RAs-Minority Mentoring, 1991-1998 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Minority Faculty/Student Recruitment, Human Ecology/Hunter Exchanges, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- Recruiting Minority Grad Students via Summer Fellowships, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Minority Faculty Recruitment: Effective Strategies-Affirmative Action, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 36)
- College Faculty Seminar-Ethnic/Cultural Factors in Research, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Historical Overview of College Changes 1965-1970- Report to Dean, November 1995 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- College Statement for Incoming President, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- College Statement on the Public Access to Research Data from Grants, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Evaluation Report-College Affirmative Action Program, 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Graduate Student Recruitment, Summer Fellowships, 1990-1996 (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Family Life Development Center (FLDC)-Dean's Advisory Committee, 1991-1992 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- FLDC Director Search, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
- FLDC Director Search-First Search, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 47-48)
- FLDC Director Search-Re-opened, 1993-1994 (Box 4, Folder 98)
- FLDC -Advisory Committee, 1994-1996 (Box 4, Folder 50)
- Studies for Cornell Nursery School, 1972-1974 (Box 10, Folder 23)
- Studies for Cornell Nursery School, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 24-25)
- Poster Submission - Maternal and Family Predictors of School Readiness, 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 26)
- Poster Submission - Correcting for Gestation Age in Infant Developmental Testing, 1988, 1989 (Box 10, Folder 27)
- Panel on Parenting, 2003 (Box 10, Folder 28)
- Ricciuti Lectures, 2004-2010 (Box 4, Folder 51)
- Series IX. Proposals, Studies, Research
- Categorization Paper, 1999-2006 (Box 5, Folder 1-12)
- Sorting Studies, 1962-1998 (Box 5, Folder 13-25)
- Research Programs in Early Development and Education, 1967-1974 (Box 5, Folder 26-39)
- Ricciuti/Breitmeyer Studies, 1978-1980 (Box 5, Folder 40-42)
- NIH Proposal, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 43)
- Rural Poor Study, 1984-1989 (Box 5, Folder 44-47)
- Crowding Study, 2002-2005 (Box 5, Folder 48)
- Research Consulting, 1983-1994 (Box 5, Folder 49-53)
- USDA- WICF Child Impact Study Technical Advisory Panel, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 54)
- Comprehensive Child Development Programs, 1993-1996 (Box 5, Folder 55)
- Program Review-University of Connecticut, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 56)
- Bronfenbrenner Life Course Center-Proposal Reviews, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 57)
- Book Review-"the Man in the Scientist", 1952 (Box 5, Folder 58)
- Reviews of Journal Manuscripts Submitted for Publication, 1986-1994 (Box 5, Folder 59)
- Single Parent Research, 1995-2008 (Box 10, Folder 1-9)
- Coding-Rural Poor Study, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 29)
- Rural Poor Study Code Book, Variable List, 1986-1992 (Box 10)
- Series X. Photographs
- Society for Research in Child Development (SRCD) Summer Institute at Cornell, June 1984 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Protein Energy and Mental Development Meeting in Bellagio, Italy- to review INCAP, Guatemala Studies, July 1990 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- International Workshop on Nutrition and Child Development at the University of Baroda, India, November 1982 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Two Photos of Henry Ricciuti, 1980s and 1960s (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Cornell Countryman, January 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- HDFS Department- photo taken on the steps of Baker Lab during Henry's second term as Department Chair, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series XI. Publications
- "Adverse Social and Biological Influences on Early Development" - by Ricciuti, 1976? (Box 2, Folder 14)
- "A Good Beginning For Babies: Guidelines for Group Care" - by Ricciuti and Anne Willis, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- "A Case Study of a University's Pattern of Error" - paper by Allan P. Sindler of Cornell, presented at annual meeting of the American Political Science Association, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Reprint List (Box 10, Folder 10)
- Publications, 1951-1953 (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Publications, 1954-1957 (Box 10, Folder 12)
- Publications, 1960s (Box 10, Folder 13)
- Publications, 1970-1973 (Box 10, Folder 14)
- Publications, 1974-1979 (Box 10, Folder 15)
- Publications, 1980s (Box 10, Folder 16)
- Publications, 1990-1994 (Box 10, Folder 17)
- Publications, 1995-2008 (Box 10, Folder 18)
- Comments on Cornell 1969, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 19)
- "When Research Findings and Social Norms Collide" - Publication History, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 20)
- Policy Constraints on Research Reporting - Background to Paper, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 21)
- Akron Paper, 2007-2008 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Series XII. Correspondence, Correspondence
- From U.S. Army to Fordham University - Instructor, PhD Thesis, Job Search, 1946-1948 (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Fordham University to University of Connecticut, 1948-1949 (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Educational Testing Service (Princeton), 1949-1953 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Exploring Position Change - From Educational Testing Service, Princeton, 1952-1954 (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Move to Colorado, 1953-1954 (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Exploring Job Openings from the University of Colorado, 1956-1957 (Box 8, Folder 6)
- University of Colorado, Child Research Council, 1955-1958 (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Move from University of Colorado; Cornell - Appointment to Associate Professor, 1957-1959 (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Return to Denver, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Court Brief in Child Custody (Biological vs. "Adoptive" Mother), 1960 (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Appointment to Full Professor, 1958-1965 (Box 8, Folder 11)
- NIMH Senior Stipend Award- Sabbatic -London, 1964-1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1971-1981 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Correspondence, 1982-1986 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1986-1994 (Box 8, Folder 15)
- New York Times Letter, September 21, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 16)
- Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 8, Folder 17)
- Correspondence, 1997-2000 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Correspondence, 2001-2003 (Box 8, Folder 19)
- Correspondence, 2004-2006 (Box 8, Folder 19A)
- Series XIII. Subject Files
- Vitas, Bibliography, 1953-2008 (Box 8, Folder 20)
- Appointment to Cornell, 1966-1995 (Box 8, Folder 21)
- Annual Reports, 1969-1998 (Box 8, Folder 22)
- Trip Reports - Bogota and Caracas, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 23)
- Awards and Sabbatical Information, 1957-2001 (Box 8, Folder 24)
- Retirement Symposium, October 1989 (Box 8, Folder 25)
- Emeriti Professor Advisory Council, 1994-2004 (Box 8, Folder 26)
- CAPE Survey, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 27)
- Professor Lee Lee, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 28)
- Ithaca City School District - Steve Hamilton, 2007-2008 (Box 8, Folder 29)
- Minority Faculty Recruitment, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 30)
- Research Proposal - NIH, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 31)
- Universal Pre-K, 2008 (Box 8, Folder 32)
- Series XIV. National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD)
- NICHD Steering Committee and Publications and Papers, 1991-2008 (Box 8, Folder 33-44)
- Memos, notes and correspondence from service as chairman of the Steering Committee guiding the study (1989-05-1991-05)and subsequently as a member of the Advisory Board appointed by and reporting to the Director of the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (1991-08-2005-05), 1989-2005 (Box 9)